<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Charterhouse with the last vvill and testament of Thomas Sutton Esquire. Taken out of the Prerogatiue Court, according to the true originall.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1614</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18506</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5056</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107783</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843478</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843478</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8217</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18506)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8217)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 830:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Charterhouse with the last vvill and testament of Thomas Sutton Esquire. Taken out of the Prerogatiue Court, according to the true originall.</title>
                  <author>Sutton, Thomas, 1532-1611. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 12, 15-22, [2], 29, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by George Eld] for Thomas Thorp,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1614.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>"The last vvill and testament. of Thomas Sutton Esquire" has separate divisional title and pagination; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charterhouse (London, England) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8217:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8217:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHARTERHOVSE <hi>WITH</hi> THE LAST VVILL <hi>and Teſtament of</hi> THOMAS SVTTON ESQVIRE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Taken out of the Prerogatiue Court,</hi> according to the true Originall.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>Thomas Thorp.</hi> 1614.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:8217:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8217:2"/>
            <head>THE CHARTER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HOVSE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HARITIE, of the three Theologicall Vertues, by the vncomptrolable teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> the greateſt, hath in theſe our daies, vpon whom are (or may be ſuppoſed to haue been) come the ends of the World, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them all, of all ſorts hath beene leaſt regarded. The conſciences of ſome particular perſons, ſealed with the true ſeales of peace and puritie, to their owne euerlaſting comfort, and the ſenſible good of their fellow-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers remaining, haue left to poſteritie notable markes of their godly deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8217:3"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> followed.</p>
            <p>This <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> dooers, agrees well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, where (euery <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> according to the workes hee hath done in his bodie) it is ſaid, <hi>few ſhall bee ſaued.</hi> Indeed it is not to be meruailed at, that <hi>Charitie waxeth cold</hi> in theſe times, where Auatice hath got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the vpper hand; <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe long ſince prophecying, that towards the end of the World it ſhould bee ſo. All States generally are corrupted: each man preferring his owne priuate inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, before the common care of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed brethren; not meaſuring any thing, but by the rule of his owne profit.</p>
            <p>To inſiſt longer vpon theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon places would bee ouer-tedious to the Reader; and not much auaileable, but rather hurtfull, as wherein he may behold the Worlds miſerable thrift,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8217:3"/>and ſo become a ſectator thereof, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt in the meane while hee make ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke of his Conſcience, and hazard the perdition of Heauen and his owne Soule. Let vs therefore walke into the Valley of Lillies, where <hi>Chriſt</hi> with his true and euerlaſting delights is ready to entertaine vs.</p>
            <p>Herevnto wiſhes alone auaile not; though in themſelues commendable. <hi>Quiddam altius in deſiderio: There is ſomething more to be deſired.</hi> With this godly deſire wee muſt ioyne ſanctitie. Holineſſe of life is it, whereby wee are acceptable <hi>before God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Naturally wee are inclined, to wiſh well to our owne ſelues. <hi>Nemo odit ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſuam.</hi> But to this well-being, well-doing is required. <hi>Quid oportet me fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere,</hi> was well propounded by that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Conuertite in the Actes; <hi>What muſt I doe, to attaine euerlaſting life?</hi> For to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8217:4"/>this end by the free grace of God we are deliuered from the bondage of Sinne and Death, That wee may <hi>ſerue him in holineſſe.</hi> Surely the yoke of the old Law was inſupportable; in reſpect of fleſh: yet that yoke was not ſo taken off by our Sauiour, that we ſhould thinke our ſelues free from all manner of yoke. <hi>Iugum meum dulce &amp; leue, My yoke is ſweet and light;</hi> yet a yoke. Hee that ſuſtaines the VVorld, beares part with vs: therefore an eaſie yoke. As eaſie notwithſtanding as it is, few vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe it. How culpable therefore the moſt part of Mankinde is, in refuſing to be coupled in this ſweet yoke, and to draw together with <hi>Christ,</hi> who beares the heauieſt part thereof, it is more than to be lamented.</p>
            <p>Not a fountaine, but an Ocean of teares, is here to be deſired; to waſh away this guilt. <hi>Ex fructibus, by their
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8217:4"/>fruits you ſhall know them,</hi> is the <hi>Cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance,</hi> whereby the good are diſcerned from the bad: the ſureſt marke of all others, whereby either God, or Sathan may claime their owne.</p>
            <p>If therefore wee would be accounted and taken for the true ſeruants of God, we muſt weare his cogniſance: wee muſt labour to make our Election ſure, by bringing forth ſuch fruits, as pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from <hi>a faith working by Loue.</hi> But this Badge is ſo ſeldome ſeene among vs, as it may well be ſuppoſed, that God hath heere but a very few ſeruants.</p>
            <p>Let vs deſire the Almightie for his great Loue to Mankinde, that hee will more and more kindle the ſmall ſparke of Charitie that is amongſt vs, that it may breake forth into a bright flame of brotherly loue, and wholly involue vs in the zeale of Gods Houſe. Then may wee ioyfully burne incenſe to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8217:5"/>the GOD of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and offer vp our vowes without feare. For the merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man hath caſt his bread vpon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny waters: and the Lord hath aſſured him a reward.</p>
            <p>Now it is time to commend to poſteritie, the due praiſes of that truely worthy and neuer to bee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Gentleman, Maiſter <hi>Thomas Sutton,</hi> the right <hi>Phoenix</hi> of Charitie in our times: who mounting vp to the higheſt top of Gods holy Hill, and gathering together the Aromaticall ſpices of Loue and Compaſsion, hath conſumed himſelfe in the fire of fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent zeale towards Gods poore Saints, who ſetting all worldly reſpects, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Alliance or Conſanguinitie, farre behinde his Loue to God and his poore brethren in <hi>Christ,</hi> hath made them (in effect) the Heyres of all thoſe great riches, wherewith it
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8217:5"/>pleaſed the Lord to bleſſe him. This godly Act of his hath herein eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally approoued it ſelfe, for that hee neuer ſtucke at any coſt, nor let ſlip any occaſion, which might further, or eſtabliſh it, to the benefit of the poore people.</p>
            <p>The greatneſſe of the gift, and the religious care taken for confirmation thereof, with the pious forwardnes of our good Soueraigne in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of ſo good a VVorke; are at large ſet foorth in a more full Volume, amongſt many other no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Reports, by a Reuerend, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, and learned Iudge of this Land: whereunto, when it ſhall be publiſhed, I referre the courteous Reader for his more ample ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. In the meane time briefly take this.</p>
            <p>The late diſſolued Charter-houſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8217:6"/>by Smithfield, not long ſince belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Right Honourable <hi>Thomas</hi> Earle of Suffolke, Lord Chamberlaine of the Kings houſhold, is well knowne to bee a very large and goodly Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; beautified with ſpacious Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, VValkes, Orchards, and other pleaſures; enriched with diuers de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendencies of Lands and Tenements therevnto belonging, and very fitly ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for wholeſome ayre, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commodities.</p>
            <p>This commodiouſneſs of ſyte, and largeneſſe of circuite, gaue occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to this worthily renowned Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman Maiſter <hi>Sutton,</hi> to affect this Houſe, as the onely fit place, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to lay the foundation of his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious deſſeignes. For hee had before that time a ſetled determination to erect an Houſe in <hi>Hallingbury Bouchers</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> to be an Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8217:6"/>for ſuch poore Men and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren as Hee himſelfe in his life time, or the future Gouernours of the ſame Hoſpitall, ſhould nominate and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point to bee lodged and relieued there: As alſo for a Schoole-Maiſter and V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher to teach the Children to reade and write, and inſtruct them in their La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine and Greeke Grammar: for a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine likewiſe, to preach the VVord of God vnto them all, and for one Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to gouerne all thoſe people belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to that Houſe.</p>
            <p>And to that end &amp; purpoſe, He had, vpon earneſt Petition, procured him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ability by Vertue of an Act of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, begun &amp; holden by prorogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on therof at Weſtminſter in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Middleſex the 9. day of February in the ſeuenth yeare of his Maieſties raigne ouer <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. and there con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to the 24. day of <hi>Iuly</hi> then next
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8217:7"/>following. To erect &amp; build in the ſaid Towne of <hi>Hallingbury Bouchers</hi> ſuch an houſe for an Hoſpital, as is immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before remembred: and that the ſaid Houſe ſhould be called <hi>The Hoſpitall of King</hi> Iames, <hi>founded in Hallingbury in the Countie of Eſſex, at the humble Petition, and at the onely coſts and charges of</hi> Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Sutton Eſquire. And that the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> that then was, and other Reuerend Praelats of this Realm, and their Succeſſors in their ſeuerall Seas, the right Honorable <hi>Thomas Lord Elleſmere,</hi> Lord Chancellor of <hi>England,</hi> and ſuch as ſhould ſucceed after him to be Lo: Chancellors or L: Keepers of the Great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> the Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer that then was, &amp; thoſe that ſhould ſucceed in that Office, with diuers other ſelect perſons both of the Clergie and Laity, in ſuch manner as you ſhall find them ſet downe in the ſaid Volume of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8217:7"/>Reports whereunto I referre you, were by the ſaid Act of Parliament elected, nominated, and appointed the firſt and preſent Gouernours of the Lands, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsions, reuenues, and goods of the ſaid Hoſpitall. But afterwards, vpon more mature deliberation, finding this great Manſion of the <hi>Charter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe,</hi> farre more conuenient for his purpoſe, then that of <hi>Hallingburie</hi> could bee, Hee was an earneſt ſutor to my Lord of <hi>Suffolk</hi> to buy that Houſe of him: acquainting his Lordſhip with the change of his minde concerning <hi>Hallingburie,</hi> and his great affection to make the <hi>Charter-houſe</hi> his Hoſpitall. To this Petition of his, it is not to bee doubted, but that my Lord gaue the more ready and willing way: becauſe the chiefe end thereof was the glorie of God, and the reliefe and comfort of a great number of poore people.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8217:8"/>Long the matter was not debated be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them: but the price being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, the Bargaine and ſale was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured. The ſumme disburſed for this purchaſe, came to thirteene thouſand pounds: which was paid down in hand, before the conueyance was ſealed.</p>
            <p>Hauing thus aſſured the ſtate of this great Houſe to him, and his Heyres, He makes humble ſuite to his Maieſtie, to grant him licence to erect and eſtabliſh his intended Hoſpitall and Grammat Schoole, and other his godly &amp; charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vſes, in the ſaid late diſſolued <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terhouſe;</hi> as in a more co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modious place, then that of <hi>Hallingbury.</hi> Herevnto the King readily yeelded; being graciouſly affected to ſo charitable a worke.</p>
            <p>The better therfore to encourage and enable this Heroicall Gentleman, to proſequute this good minde to the full perfection; it pleaſed his Maieſtie out
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8217:8"/>of his moſt Royall diſpoſition, to grant his Letters patents vnto him, thereby au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſing him to the vſes laſt mentioned, as in his Letters pattents more fully ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth.</p>
            <p>Now therefore with alacritie this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes goes forwards. The Reuerend Father in God, <hi>George</hi> now Arch-biſhop of <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury, Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Elleſmere,</hi> Lord Chancellor of <hi>England, Robert</hi> Earle of <hi>Salisburie,</hi> Lord high Treaſurer of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Iohn</hi> the elect Biſhop of London, <hi>Lancelot</hi> now Biſhop of <hi>Ely,</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Cooke</hi> Knight, cheefe Iuſtice of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon pleas, Sir <hi>Thomas Foſter</hi> Knight, one of his Maieſties Iuſtices of the common plees, Sir <hi>Henry Hobart</hi> Knight and Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, Atturney generall, <hi>Iohn Ouerall</hi> now Deane of the Cathedral Church of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in London, <hi>George Mountaine</hi> Deane of the Collegiat Church of Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, <hi>Henry Thurſby</hi> Eſquire, one of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8217:9"/>Maſters of the <hi>Chancerle, Geffrey Nightin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gale</hi> Eſquire, <hi>Richard Sutton</hi> Eſquire, <hi>Iohn Law</hi> Gentleman, <hi>Thomas Browne</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and the Maſter of the Hoſpitall of King <hi>Iames,</hi> founded in Charterhouſe, within the Countie of Middleſex, at the humble Petition and the onely coſts and charges of <hi>Thomas Sutton</hi> Eſquire, are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, nominated, and ordained by the Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie in his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Patents granted (as aforeſaid) the firſt Gouernors of the Lands, Poſſeſſions, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenues, and Goods of the ſaid Hoſpitall of King <hi>Iames</hi> founded in <hi>Charterhouſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further power is giuen to the ſaid Gouernours, as you may find more at large in the ſaid Letters Patents.</p>
            <p>Herevpon diuers Lands, by him for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly purchaſed, are made and paſt ouer to this Hoſpitall, for maintenance of the poore people there to be relieued. Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is made for fit lodgings, and other
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8217:9"/>neceſſaries; and all things goe onwards, with as conuenient ſpeed as may be, to the wiſhed end.</p>
            <p>Now for the Readers better informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and content, it will not be amiſſe to ſet downe, what Lands they were, and in what Counties, which were made o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and annexed by Maiſter <hi>Sutton</hi> to the ſaid Hoſpitall. Thus therefore they are named, as they follow in order: <hi>(viz.)</hi> All thoſe his Mannors and Lordſhips of <hi>Southminster, Norton, Little Hallingbury,</hi> alias <hi>Hallingbury Bouchers,</hi> and <hi>Much Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſsex,</hi> with all their and euery of their rights, members, and appurtenances whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>Alſo all thoſe his Mannors and Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips of <hi>Baſtingthorpe,</hi> alias <hi>Buſlingthorpe</hi> and <hi>Dunneſby</hi> in the County of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> with their &amp; euery of their rights, mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and appurtenances whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>Alſo thoſe his Mannors of <hi>Salthorp</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:8217:10"/>alias <hi>Saltrop</hi> alias <hi>Haltrop, Chilton,</hi> and <hi>Blackgroue,</hi> in the County of <hi>Wilts,</hi> with their and euery of their rights, mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and appurtenances: and alſo all thoſe his lands &amp; paſture grounds called <hi>Blackgroue,</hi> containing by eſtimation two hundred acres of paſture with the appur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances in <hi>Blackgroue</hi> and <hi>Wroughton,</hi> in the ſaid County of <hi>Wilts:</hi> and alſo all that his Mannor of <hi>Miſsenden,</hi> otherwiſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Mannor of <hi>Miſſunden,</hi> in the Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes of <hi>Wroughton, Lydierde,</hi> and <hi>Tregoſe</hi> in the ſaid County of <hi>Wilts,</hi> with all his rights, members, and appurtenances.</p>
            <p>And all that his Mannor of <hi>Elcombe</hi> and <hi>Parke</hi> called <hi>Elcombe Parke,</hi> with the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purtenances, in the ſaid County of <hi>Wilts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alſo All that his Mannor of <hi>Watleſcote,</hi> alias <hi>Wigleſcete,</hi> alias <hi>Wigleſcete</hi> with the appurtenances in the ſaid County of <hi>Wilts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And alſo All that his Mannor of <hi>Weſcote</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:8217:10"/>alias <hi>Weſete,</hi> with the appurtenances, in the ſaid County of <hi>Wilts:</hi> and alſo al thoſe his lands and paſtures, containing by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimation 100. acres of land, &amp; 60. acres of paſture with the appurtenances in <hi>Wig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſcote</hi> &amp; <hi>Wroughton</hi> in the ſaid County of <hi>Wilts:</hi> and All that his Mannor of <hi>Vffcote</hi> with the appurtenances in the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Wilts:</hi> and alſo al thoſe his two Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuages, &amp; one thouſand acres of land, two thouſand acres of paſture, three hundred acres of Meadow, and three hundred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cres of wood with the appurtenances, in <hi>Brodehinton</hi> in the ſaid County of <hi>Wilts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And alſo All thoſe the Mannors and Lordſhips of <hi>Campes,</hi> alias <hi>Campes Castle,</hi> otherwiſe called <hi>Caſtle Campes</hi> with the appurtenances, ſcituare, lying, being, and extending in the Counties of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi> and <hi>Eſſex,</hi> or in either of them, or elſewhere within the Realme of <hi>England,</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:8217:11"/>
            <p>And alſo all that his Mannor of <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham,</hi> in the County of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> with all &amp; ſingular the rights, members &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purtenances thereof whatſoeuer. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo All thoſe his Meſſuages and Lands ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuate, lying, and being in the Pariſhes of <hi>Hackuey</hi> and <hi>Tottenham</hi> in the County of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> or in either of them, with their and euery of their rights, members, and appurtenances whatſoeuer, which ſaid Meſſuage was lately purchaſed of Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Bowyer</hi> Knight; &amp; the ſaid Lands in <hi>Tottenham</hi> now or lately were in the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure or occupation of <hi>William Benning</hi> Yeoman. And alſo All and ſingular the Mannors, Lordſhips, Meſſuages, Lands, Tenements, Reuerſions, Seruices, Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, Paſtures, Woods, Aduouſons, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronages of Churches, &amp; Hereditaments of the ſaid <hi>Thomas Sutton</hi> whatſoeuer, ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuat, lying, or being within the ſaid coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Eſſex, Lincoln, Wilts, Cambridge,</hi> and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8217:11"/>
               <hi>Middleſex,</hi> or in any of them, with all and euery of their rights, members, &amp; appur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances whatſoeuer. (Except All his Mannors or Lordſhips of <hi>Littlebury</hi> and <hi>Haddeſtockc</hi> with their appurtenances, in the ſaid County of <hi>Eſſex.</hi>) But alas, what perpetuity can bee looked for in this world; where there is no certainty but of change. In this great expectation of all men, whileſt our eyes and mindes are oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied with admiration of the Worke, Death ſteales away, the Maſter worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: but not vnprouided; as hauing his <hi>Viaticum</hi> ſealed vp vnto him in the peace of a good conſcience. Many prayers of the Saint went vp before him, to prepare a place for him againſt the day of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution: and the corruptible <hi>Mammon,</hi> which he had here imployed to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of Gods ſeruants in Earth, begot him friends to entertaine him in heauen. So he fell aſleepe in the Lord: leauing the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8217:12"/>reſt of his pious intendments, to bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by his truſtie Executors, Maſter <hi>Richard Sutton,</hi> and Maiſter <hi>Iohn Lawe. Behold,</hi> here a perfect <hi>Iſraelite!</hi> This is a good worke: but he hath not ſet his reſt on this onely. He hath growne vp from faith to faith, to the accompliſhment of many other ſingular workes of Charitie: whereof his laſt Will and Teſtament giues ſuch abundant teſtimonie, that it needs no other ſplendour than it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Vpon this reſpect, I will make no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Proeme to it, than a gentle inuitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Reader to peruſe it; leſt other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I might ſeeme to ſhew the Sunne at Noone Day; or perſwade credit, to appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent demonſtration. Thus it followeth.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="will">
            <pb facs="tcp:8217:12"/>
            <head>THE <hi>LAST VVILL</hi> and Teſtament. <hi>OF</hi> Thomas Sutton Eſquire.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:8217:13"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8217:13"/>
            <head>THE LAST VVILL and Teſtament of <hi>Thomas Sutton Eſquire.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N THE NAME OF GOD AMEN.</p>
            <p>THE Second day of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uember in the yeare of out Lord God one thouſand ſixe hundred and ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen <hi>I Thomas Sutton</hi> of Camps Caſtell in the County of Cambridge Eſquire being weake in body, and of good perfect mind and me mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thankes be giuen to Almighty God for the ſame: Do make and declare this my laſt Will and Teſtament in manner and forme following that is to ſay. Firſt, and principally I commend my Soule into the handes of Almighty God
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8217:14"/>truſting through his mercy &amp; by the pretious death and paſſion of my Sauiour and Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Ieſus Christ</hi> to bee ſaued and to inherit the kingdome of Heauen for euer. And my body I will to be buried where and in what ſort it ſhall ſeeme meet and conuenient to mine Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutor or Executors and Superuiſor or Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſors of this my laſt will and Teſtament, with the leaſt pomp and charge that may be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to euery one of the Children of <hi>Richard Coxe</hi> late Biſhop of Ely who ſhall bee liuing at the time of my death, Ten-poundes a peece, of lawfull mony of England.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to the Children of <hi>Ellenor Aske</hi> late wife of <hi>Robert Aske</hi> of Aughton in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye of york Eſquire the ſumme of one hundred poundes of good and lawfull mony of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland to bee equally diſtributed amongſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to the poore towne of Berwicke vppon Tweede one hundreth markes of lawful mony of England to be diſtributed amongſt the poore there by the diſcretion of the chiefe gouernour and Preacher there for the time being to be paid within one yeare after my deceaſe.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:8217:14"/>
            <p>Alſo I giue to <hi>Andrew Weſtwoods</hi> wife of New Caſtle vpon Tyne, or to her Children, or to ſo many of them as ſhall be liuing at my death, ten poundes, to be beſtowed equally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them.</p>
            <p>And I giue to the poore people of Stoke-Newington, in the County of Middleſex Ten-pounds to be diſtributed by the Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, Church-wardens, &amp; Parſon of the ſame Town, for the time being to their moſt needy, people there,</p>
            <p>Alſo I giue to Maiſter <hi>Gray</hi> dwelling in york<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire, ſometimes ſeruant to <hi>Ambroſe</hi> Earle of Warwick or to his Children if any of them bee liuing at my deceaſe Forty poundes of good and lawful mony of England, to be diſtributed equally amongſt them, within ſixe monthes after my deceaſe.</p>
            <p>Alſo I giue to the Children of my Aunt <hi>White</hi> or to ſo many of them as ſhall bee liuing at my deceaſe, one hundred markes to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually diſtributed amongſt them within ſixe monethes next after my deceaſe.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:8217:15"/>
            <p>Alſo I giue to <hi>William Cocket</hi> ſonne to <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Cocket,</hi> late Alderman of the Citty of Lincolne one hundreth pounds of lawfull mony of England.</p>
            <p>Alſo I giue to the Children of <hi>Iohn Copeland</hi> late of Skillingthorpe in the County of Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne or to ſo many of them as ſhall be liuing at the time of my deceaſe, one hundred pounds of lawfull money of England, to bee equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſtributed amongſt them ſauing vnto <hi>Elizabeth Copeland,</hi> for my meaning is that ſhe ſhall not haue any part of the ſaid Legacy of one hundred pounds.</p>
            <p>And vnto the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Copeland</hi> I giue the ſumme of one hundreth pounds, of lawful mony of England to be paid vnto her at the day of her marriage, or within one yeare after my deceaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue vnto <hi>Iane Vpton</hi> one of the Daughters of <hi>Elizabeth Vpton</hi> late wife of <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond Vpton</hi> of Wamfleet in the County of Lincolne <hi>Eſquire,</hi> the ſumme of fifty pounds of Lawful mony of England.</p>
            <p>And to euery other of the Children of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8217:15"/>ſaid <hi>Elizabeth</hi> who ſhall be liuing at the time of my deceaſe twenty poundes a peece of lawfull money of England, to bee paid with in ſixe monthes next after my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe.</p>
            <p>Alſo I giue to the Children of one <hi>Skelton</hi> late of Lowth in the County of Lincolne and ſomtimes towards the Henneages of Heniton in the ſaid County tenne poundes to be equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deuided amongſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to the Children of <hi>Thomas Pyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> late of Mitcham in the County of Surrey Eſquire or to ſo many of them as ſhall be liu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at my deceaſe, twenty poundes to bee equally diſtributed amongſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to the Children of <hi>Henry Tutty</hi> late Gunner in Barwick, or to ſo many of them as ſhall bee liuing at my deceaſe ten poundes of lawful mony of England to be equally diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed amongſt them.</p>
            <p>Alſo I giue to my Neece <hi>Elizabeth Allen,</hi> two hundred poundes of lawfull mony of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:8217:16"/>
            <p>And to euery of her Children which ſhall be liuing at my deceaſe one hundreth markes a peece.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to <hi>Symon Baxter</hi> if he bee liuing at my deceaſe, three hundred pounds of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful mony of England, if not then I giue the ſame ſumme to his Child or Children to be equally deuided amongſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue vnto <hi>Francis Baxter</hi> if he bee li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing at my death fiue hundred markes of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mony of England if not I giue the ſame ſum to his Child or Children to bee equally deuided amongſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue vnto each of my ſeruingmen to whom I giue wages with my Cooke that ſhall be aliue at my deceaſe thirteene pound ſixe ſhillings and eight pence ouer and aboue their wages then due.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to ſo many of my maidſeruants as I haue in my houſe at the time of my deceaſe fiue markes a apeece ouer and aboue their wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue vnto the Children of <hi>Reinold
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8217:16"/>Tomps</hi> my late ſeruant if any of them bee aliue at my death ten pounds to bee diſtributed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to the Fyſhermen of the Towne of Oaſtend in the Low Cuntries one hundred poundes of lawful Engliſh money to be giuen and diſtributed amongſt the pooreſt fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of that Towne or for want of a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent number of them to call in ſome other of that Towne to haue a ſhre of the ſaid one hundred poundes by the diſcretion of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours of that Towne and his aſſiſtants and the Parſon and Miniſter there for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame to be paid within one yeare after my deceaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue towards the mending of the High-waies betweene Iſlington and Newing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton in the County of Middleſex Twenty ſixe poundes thirteene ſhillings and fower pence of lawful mony of England to bee imployed and beſtowed by the good ouerſight of mine Executor or Executors the Cunſtable of Newington and the Churchwardens there for the time being the ſame Highwayes to bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended made and holpen within one yeare af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my deceaſe.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:8217:17"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue towards the amending of the of highwaes betweene Aſhden and Walden in the County of Eſſex called Walden Lane one hundreth poundes of Lawfull mony of England. And towardes the amending of the highwaies between great Lynton in the Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Cambridge and the ſaid Towne of Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den three skore ſixe pounds thirteen ſhillings and foure pence of lawfull mony of England: And I alſo giue towards the amending of Horſeth-Lane threeskore poundes of lawfull money of England.</p>
            <p>All theſe workes next before recited I will ſhall be ouerſeene and guided by the two head Conſtables therevnto next adioyning the Treſorer of Walden and the Parſonnes of Aſhden Hadſtock and Horſheath and the Conſtables of the ſame Pariſhes for the time being: And the ſame ſeueral ſummes to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed and the ſaid High-waies ſo to be amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſo farre as the ſame ſummes will extend within one yeare after my deceaſe.</p>
            <p>Alſo I giue towards the amending of the Bridges and the ordinary high wayes between South minſter and Malden in the ſaid County Eſſex the ſumme of one hundred poundes of lawfull money of England and the ſame worke
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8217:17"/>to be ouerſeene and guided by the two head Conſtables therevnto next adioyning and the parſons or Vicars of South-minſter and Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den for the time being and the ſame money to be ſo employed and the high waies ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended within one yeere next after my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> I giue to Maiſter <hi>Robert Dudley</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman of Newcaſtle vpon Tyne or to his Children or to ſo many of his Children as ſhall bee liuing at the time of my deceaſe Thirty pounds of lawfull money of England which hee oweth me.</p>
            <p>And I will and doe earneſtly charge mine Executor or Executors to deliuer into the Treſurie or Chamber of the Citie of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don one Thouſand pounds in currant mony of England with ſuch care and foreſight to be had that ſuch bonds or aſſurances bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the Lord Maior and Aldermen of the ſame Citie that for the time ſhall bee by learned Counſell in the Law as the ſame may bee ſafe and for euer goe and bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted to theſe vſes following: That is to ſay that the ſaid thouſand pounds be yeerely lent and put foorth to ten yonge Marchant
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8217:18"/>men not hauing any great ſtockes of their owne being yong men and of honeſt life and conuerſation and towardly in their trades that is to euery one of them one hundreth pounds for a yeare without paying any thing for the ſame; And theſe ten yong Marchants to bee choſen and appointed by the Lord Maior and Aldermen of the ſaid Citie that for the time ſhall bee and the Deane of the Cathedrall Church of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in London for the time beeing. Prouided as before that none haue or continue the ſaid hundred pounds ſo appointed aboue one yeare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> I will and giue to the Children of <hi>Iuſtinian Crome</hi> Draper ſometimes dwelling in the Citie of Lincolne or to his childrens children if any of them ſhall be liuing at my deceaſe Twenty pounds of lawfull money of England to bee equally diuided amongſt them.</p>
            <p>I giue alſo to the Wife and Children or Child of <hi>Martine VVatherſine</hi> Dutchman, ſometime dwelling at the ſigne of the White Beare in Buttolph Lane London if any of them be liuing at the time of my death Ten
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8217:18"/>pounds to bee equally diuided amongſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> I giue to the next kinſman or kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman of <hi>Henry Vauering</hi> Dutchman Smith ſomtimes dwelling in Barwick three pounds ſix ſhillings eight pence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue and bequeath vnto Sir <hi>Francis Popham</hi> Knight as well in reſpect and good will which I beare vnto his Wife beeing the Daughter of my late deceaſed deare Wife the ſumme of two thouſand Markes of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full money of England vpon condition ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe and ſo that the ſaid Sir <hi>Francis Popham</hi> and the ſaid Ladie <hi>Anne</hi> his Wife giue a ſufficient diſcharge and a generall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe to mine Executor or Executors as well for that ſumme as alſo for the receipt of all the reſt of her part of portion of the plate money and houſhould ſtuffe already paide and deliuered to them or to their vſe as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by ſeuerall bills or notes ſubſcribed with mine owne hand which I doe thinke to be the very true halfe and better halfe of the ſaid plate money and houſhould ſtuffe part whereof was deliuered by one <hi>Iohn Fiſhborne</hi> my late ſeruant to Sir <hi>Iohn Popham</hi> Knight
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8217:19"/>late Lord Chiefe Iuſtice of England at his late houſe in Chauncerie Lane, The reſt of the houſhould ſtuffe as Chaires Stooles Bedſteedes Kitchin-ſtuffe Tables &amp; ſuch like was deliuered by the ſaid <hi>Fiſhborne</hi> to the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Pophams</hi> Seruants at Newing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, one Thouſand pounds in mony paid in this ſort <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To Sir <hi>Iohn Popham</hi> by his ſeruant <hi>Straker</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> bill before marriage three hundred pounds which bill after the marriage I returned to the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Popham</hi> ſeauen hundred pounds were paid to the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Popham</hi> vpon the marriage by one Mr. <hi>Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Law</hi> late dwelling in <hi>pater noſter row</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the better moyety of the plate due to Sir <hi>Francis Popham</hi> was by the appointment of the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Popham</hi> receiued by one Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Clarke</hi> ſomtimes towardes the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> and now a Councellor at the law of the middle Temple as I gueſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to my welbeloued friend <hi>Amy Popham</hi> two hundred poundes to bee paid to her at the day of her marriage, or when ſhe ſhall accompliſh the age of eighteene yeares.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to <hi>Francis Popham Mary Popham
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8217:19"/>Elizabeth Popham Iane Popham</hi> and <hi>Anne Pop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> all daughters of the ſaid Lady <hi>Anne Pop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> one hundreth poundes a peece which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall ſummes I will ſhall be paid them at the dayes of their marriage or when they ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh the age of eighteene yeares: And my will and meaning is that vnleſſe the ſaid Sir <hi>Francis Popham</hi> and the ſaid Lady <hi>Anne</hi> his wife do or ſhall giue to mine Executor or Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors a generall acquittance or releaſe to the effect aboue mentioned that then as well the ſaid Legacy of two thouſand marks ſo wiled to bee giuen to the ſaid Sir <hi>Francis Popham</hi> and the Lady <hi>Anne</hi> his wife as alſo the other ſeuerall legacies giuen and bequeathed to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of the ſaid children of the ſaid Sir <hi>Francis Popham</hi> and the Lady his Wife ſhall remaine and be to the vſe of mine Executor or Executors to bee wholly diſpoſed and giuen by them within one yeere after my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe partly to the amending of high waies and partly to poore Maidens marriages and partly to the releaſing of poore men that lie in priſon for debt and partly to the poore people of mine intended Hoſpitall when it ſhall pleaſe God that it ſhall bee eſtabliſhed and erected. And where perhaps it is or may bee ſuppoſed that the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Popham</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:8217:20"/>hath paid three hundred poundes to Sir <hi>Rowland Hayward</hi> of the Citty of London Alderman as a debt due vnto him vppon the bondes of <hi>Iohn Dudley</hi> and <hi>Thomas Dudley</hi> I proteſt before God that I paide the whole three hundred poundes to the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Popham</hi> in this ſort to bee paid ouer to the ſaid Sir <hi>Rowland Heyward viz</hi> Two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred poundes by my ſeruant <hi>Iohn Fiſhborne</hi> and one hundred poundes by one <hi>Henry Beſt</hi> Scriuener neere: Temple-barre There was a demande made by Alderman <hi>Duckets</hi> Executors for foure hundred poundes ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſaid Alderman vppon the bondes of <hi>Iohn Dudley</hi> and <hi>Thomas Dudley</hi> for Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for the vſe of the Earle of Leceſter which the ſaide Earle tranſported into Spaine which debt was paid to the ſaid Alderman For I my ſelfe was a meſſenger from the ſaid Earle to the ſaid Alderman to let him vnderſtand that Maſter <hi>Bainham</hi> my Lords ſpeciall Officer and receuer ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge them preſently and after it was diſchar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the ſaid Alderman demanded intereſt for the forbearing of the foure hundred poundes which as I remember <hi>Thomas Dudley</hi> diſcharged: Maiſter <hi>Iuſtice Owin</hi> as I remember who had the doing in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8217:20"/>teſtament of Alderman <hi>Ducket</hi> promiſed to deliuer in the ſaid bond to Sir <hi>Iohn Popham</hi> then being Attorney which I doe beleeue hee did: And where Maiſter <hi>Iohn Gardiner</hi> brother to my late wife by his laſt Will and Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment did giue vnto <hi>Anne Dudley</hi> now Wife to Sir <hi>Francis Popham</hi> one hundred poundes to be paid to her at the day of her marriage the ſame hundred poundes was and is paid by me at or before the day of her marriage <hi>videlicet.</hi> In a Chaine of Golde beeing foureſcore ſeauenteene poundes tenne ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linges in Golde and for the faſhion paid to Maiſter <hi>Podmore</hi> Goldſmith in London fifty ſhillinges which compleates the hundred pounds for the which amonſt other thinges which I deliuered in truſt I haue no acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to Maiſter <hi>Ieffery Nightingale</hi> Eſquire the ſome of forty poundes of lawfull money of England.</p>
            <p>Alſo I giue to my Coſen <hi>William Stapleton</hi> ſonne of Sir <hi>Richard Stapleton</hi> Knight one hundred markes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item,</hi> I giue vnto the Children of Sir <hi>Frauncis Willoughbie</hi> Knight one
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8217:21"/>hundred poundes of lawfull money of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland to bee equally diſtributed amongſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue vnto <hi>Iohn Law</hi> one of the Procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators of the Arches London two hundred poundes,</p>
            <p>And to Maiſter <hi>Thomas Browne</hi> ten pounds to make him a Ring.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to the wife and Children of <hi>Iohn Gardiner</hi> my late wifes Nephew if they be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing after my deceaſe being the mother and two ſonnes two hundred markes to be equally deuided amongſt them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to the poore people of Hadſtock to be diſtributed amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens and Conſtables there for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing twenty poundes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to the poore people of Littlebury and to the poore people of Balſham to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed as afore to either Towne twenty pounds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to the Parſon and Church-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens of Balſham aforeſaid for the time being
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8217:21"/>to buy a Bell withall to be hanged vp in the Steeple to amend the Ring there twenty poundes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> to the poore of Southminſter twenty poundes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> to the poore of little Hallenbury twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty poundes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> to the poore of Dunsby in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Lincolne twenty poundes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to <hi>Robert Wright</hi> poulter of little Hallenbury fiue pound.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to widdow <hi>Aske</hi> late wife of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert Aske</hi> of London goldſmith twenty pound which ſhe oweth me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> my will and meaning is that there ſhall no intereſt or increaſe for money bee taken after my deceaſe ſo as hee or they by whom any ſummes of money are or ſhall bee owing doe pay the principall debt within one halfe yeare next after my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue and bequeath to the poore priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8217:22"/>within the Priſons of Ludgate Newgate the two Compters in London the Kinges bench and the Marſhalſea the ſumme of two hundred pounds to be paid &amp; deuided among the ſame priſoners by euen &amp; equall portions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to <hi>Suſan Price</hi> at the day of her marriage forty poundes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to one <hi>Collins</hi> of the Towne of Curſall in Eſſex fiue poundes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to my good friends Miſtris <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> and Mris. <hi>Low</hi> either of them ten pounds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to <hi>Margret Woodhall</hi> my God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daughter the ſumme of twenty poundes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to al other my God-children fiue poundes apeece.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue and bequeath to the Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and fellowes as the Corporation of <hi>Ieſus</hi> Coledge in Cambridge the ſumme of fiue hundred markes of lawfull money of England to bee imployed vſed and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed for or in ſome perpetuity for and to the vſe benefit and behalfe of the ſaid
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8217:22"/>Colledge Maiſter Fellowes and Schollers in ſuch ſort manner and forme as by the diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of the Biſhop of Elie for the time being the Vicechancellor of Cambrige for the time being the Maiſter and Fellowes of the ſaid Colledge for the time being, and my executors hereafter named or the ſuruiuor or ſuruiuors of them if they bee liuing when the beſtowing of the ſaide ſumme ſhall come in queſtion ſhalbe thought beſt and moſt conuenient.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue and bequeath to the Maiſter and Fellowes as the Corporation of Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalene Colledge in Cambridge the ſumme of fiue hundred pounds to be imployed vſed or beſtowed for or in ſome perpetuity for and to the vſe benefit and behalfe of the ſaid Colledge Maiſter and Fellowes and Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers there in ſuch ſort manner and forme as by the diſcretion priuity and conſent of the Vicechauncellor in Cambridge for the time being the Maiſter of Trinity Colledge in Cambridge for the time being and the Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and Fellowes of the ſaid Magdalene Colledge for the time being ſhalbe thought beſt and moſt conuenient.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:8217:23"/>
            <p>And I will that all my great Chaine of gold and all my Iewelles of what kind ſoeuer they be ſhalbe ſould by myne Executors and ſuperuiſors hereafter named towards the better and ſpeedier payment of my legacies and performance of this my laſt will and teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tament.</p>
            <p>And my will and meaning is that all the legacies by me in this my teſtament and laſt will giuen and bequeathed and for the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of much whereof there is no certaine time ſet down ſhalbe paid within two yeares next after my deceaſe at the furtheſt.</p>
            <p>Alſo I giue for and towards the building of mine intended Hoſpitall Chappell and Schoolehouſe the ſumme of fiue thouſand pounds if I doe not liue to ſee it performed in my life time.</p>
            <p>And I deſire in the name of GOD my Feoffes and my executor or executors with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in two yeares after my deceaſe or ſooner if they may conueniently (if it pleaſe not GOD I liue to ſee and cauſe the ſame my determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be performed and accompliſhed) to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8217:23"/>ſee and cauſe the ſame to be performed and accompliſhed</p>
            <p>Alſo I giue the reſidue of the yeares which I ſhall haue at the time of my deceaſe in one cloſe called the Withies lying within the towne and fields of Cottingham in the County of Yorke to the Maior and Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Beuerley or to the gouernor of the ſame towne and his aſſiſtants for the time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this end and purpoſe that they ſhall diſtribute or cauſe to be diſtributed the year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profit ariſing of the ſame ouer and aboue the yearely Rent payable to the Kings Maieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie amongſt the pooreſt people dwelling within the ſaid towne of Beuerley.</p>
            <p>Alſo I giue to the Maior and Alder-men of the citty of Lincolne for the time being all ſuch proffits and reuenewes as ſhal ariſe and growe of the parſonage of Glentham within the county of Lincolne and all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidue of the yeares that ſhall remaine after my deceaſe to this intent that they ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute and beſtowe or cauſe to be diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and beſtowed the ſame amongſt twenty of the pooreſt people that ſhall then bee dwelling in the ſaid citty with the conſent
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8217:24"/>and priuity of the Deane of the Cathederall Church of Lincolne or the Recorder of the ſame for the time being (they the ſaid Maior Aldermen Deane and Recorder foreſeeing that the Parſonage be letten for their moſt benefit.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue into the Treſory or Store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of mine entended Hoſpitall to begin their ſtocke with and to defend the rights of the houſe one thouſand pounds of lawfull Engliſh mony.</p>
            <p>And I giue to euery one of my Feoffees whome I haue put in truſt about my enten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Hoſpitall (to whome I haue not giuen any thing in this my laſt will) the ſumme of twenty ſixe pounds thirty ſhillings and foure pence of lawfull mony of England.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to <hi>Amy Popham</hi> if it pleaſe GOD ſhe liue to keepe houſe three Fether-beds and ſo many paire of Holland ſheetes with the boulſters to them and ſo many hangings of tapeſtry as furniſh her a bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamber The reſt of my houſhouldſtuffe I will ſhalbe ſold by myne executors for the ſpeedier payment of my leagacies and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8217:24"/>formance of this my laſt will.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to the widow <hi>Taſſell</hi> of Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham the ſumme of fiue pounds of Lawfull mony of England and to <hi>Thomas Lawrence</hi> the elder of the ſame towne fiue pounds of like lawfull mony of England.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue and bequeath vnto the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Perciuall Graung</hi> my late ſeruant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed the ſumme of twenty pounds of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mony of England.</p>
            <p>And of this my laſt will and teſtament I make and ordaine <hi>Richard Sutton</hi> of London Eſquire and <hi>Iohn Law</hi> one of the procurators of the Arches London my Executors char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them as they will anſwer at the laſt day of iudgement that they or one of them in the abſence of the other endeuor them-ſelues with all earneſtneſſe and diligence to ſee this my will performed according to my true meaning and charitable intent.</p>
            <p>And I make ouerſeers of this my laſt will and teſtament the Reuerend Father in GOD <hi>George Abbot</hi> Archbiſhop of Canterbury vnto whome I giue and bequeath the ſumme
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:8217:25"/>of forty markes of lawfull mony of England or a peece of plate of that value at his elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and choyſe.</p>
            <p>And alſo <hi>Launcelot Androes</hi> Almonizer to the Kings Maieſty my other ſuperuiſor and ouerſeer of this my laſt will and teſtament vnto whome I giue and bequeath the ſumme of twenty pounds of like lawfull mony of England or a peece of place of that value at his election and choyſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> my will and full intent and meaning is that if any perſon or perſons whoſoeuer to whome I haue in and by this my laſt will and teſtament giuen and bequeathed any leagacy or ſumme or ſummes of mony ſhall any waies gainſay impugne contradict or impeach this my laſt will and teſtament that then all and euery one ſo impugning contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting impeaching or gaineſaying this my laſt will and teſtament and euery of their children and kinsfolkes to whome I haue in and by this my laſt will and teſtament giuen and bequeathed any leagacy or ſumme or ſummes of mony ſhall haue no part nor por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any ſuch guift leagacy or bequeſt but ſhall vtterly looſe the ſame and bee vterly
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8217:25"/>barred thereof as if no ſuch Legacy gift or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt had bin giuen vnto him her or them by this my laſt will and teſtament (any thing before in theſe preſents mentioned or contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue and bequeath to <hi>Richard Sutton</hi> one of my Executors before named the ſumme of one hundred poundes, and to miſtris <hi>Law</hi> ouer and beſides the Legacy before to her gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen I giue the ſumme of forty poundes to make her a gowne withall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to Maiſter <hi>Hutton</hi> the Vicar of Littlebury twenty poundes. To the Towne of Camps Caſtle where I dwel to be diſtributed amongſt the poore of the ſame Pariſh tenne poundes.</p>
            <p>Alſo to the poore of the towne of Elcombe to be equally diſtributed amongſt them the ſumme of ten poundes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue and bequeath thoſe my mannors of Littlebury and Hadſtock in the County of Eſſex to the right honorable the Lord <hi>Thomas Howard</hi> Earle of Suffolke and to his heires for euer vpon Condition that he do wel and truly pay or cauſe to bee paid to my Executors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore named or to the ſuruiuor of them the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8217:26"/>ſumme of Tenne thouſand poundes of law full money of England within one yeare next after my deceaſe. And if he ſhall refuſe to pay the ſaid ſumme of tenne thouſand pounds for the ſaid Mannors then I giue and bequeath the ſaid Mannors of Littlebury and Hadſtock to my ſaid Executors and to their Heires for euer. And then I will and deuiſe that the ſaid Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors of Littlebury and Hadſtock ſhall bee ſold by my ſaid Executors or the ſuruiuor of them to the vttermoſt price and valew that they may be ſold for and the money comming of the ſale thereof together with as much more as ſhall make vp the ſame ſumme the full ſom of twenty thouſand poundes I will ſhall bee imployed and beſtowed by my ſaid Executors or the ſuruiuor of them with the aduiſe of my Superuiſors afore named in ſome good works and charitable vſes for mine intended Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall and for poore people or otherwiſe as they in their wiſedomes &amp; diſcretions ſhal think fit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to Maiſter <hi>Flud</hi> Parſon of New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ington the ſumme of thirteene pound ſixe ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings eigt pence: And to the wife of <hi>Beniamin King</hi> of Southminſter ſixe pound thirteene ſhillings fourepence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to <hi>Thomas Averell</hi> if it ſhall bee found that he hath dealt faithfully and plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8217:26"/>with me in my buſineſſe the ſumme of tenne poundes which he owerh me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue vnto the wife of Maiſter <hi>Ingry</hi> of Littlebury three pound ſixe ſhillings eight pence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to Sir <hi>Henry Hubberd</hi> Knight the Kinges Maieſties Attorney generall a peece of plate of the valew of ten pound: And to Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Lockſmith</hi> his Clarke the ſumme of tenne pound.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to the poore of the pariſh of Hackney ten pound.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to <hi>Bridget Law</hi> the ſumme of ten pound: And to the Lady <hi>Altham</hi> daughter to Maiſter <hi>Auditor Sutton</hi> the ſumme of twenty poundes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to Sir <hi>Edward Phillips</hi> Maiſter of the Rolles a peece of plate of the value of twenty pound: And to Sir <hi>Iames Altham</hi> one of the Barrons of the Exchequor one peece of plate of the valew of twenty pound.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to my late wiues kinſman <hi>Guy Goddolphin</hi> the ſumme of ten pound.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> I giue to the right honorable my ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good Lord the Earle of Suffolk the ſumme of foure hundred pounds. All the reſt of my
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8217:27"/>goods chattles and debtes not before giuen and diſpoſed I giue and bequeath to my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented Hoſpitall to be imployed and beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on and about the ſame according to the diſcretion of the Feoffes of my ſaid Hoſpital or the greater part of them In witnes hereof I haue here-vnto ſet my hand and ſeale the twenty eight day of the moneth of Nouem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber aboue written THOMAS SSTTON. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morandum</hi> that the ſame teſtator did acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge this his will written and contained in theſe three and twenty leaues to be his laſt will and teſtament and that his hand and ſeale ſet therevnto is his owne hand and ſeale and that he had heard it read &amp; was acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the contents of it the ſaid twenty eight of Nouember aboue written in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of vs <hi>Iohn Law Leonard Houghton Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander Longworth Thomas Hall</hi> The marke of <hi>Richard Pearce</hi> The marke of <hi>Thomas Iohnſon Primo Decembris.</hi> 1611 <hi>idem recognitum per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtatorem coram Io. Crooke. Quarto Decembris</hi> 1611 <hi>recognit.</hi> to be the Teſtators laſt wil. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me <hi>Hen. Thoresby.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Codicill to bee anexed to the laſt Will &amp; teſtament of <hi>Thomas Sutton</hi> Eſquire made and declared the day whereon he dyed being
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8217:27"/>the twelfth of December one thouſand ſixe hundred and eleuen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Item</hi> he gaue and bequeathed to Maiſter Iudge <hi>Crooke</hi> one of the Iudges of the Kinges Bench at Weſtminſter the ſumme of tenne poundes And to Maiſter <hi>Henry Thoreſby</hi> one of the Maiſters of the Court of Chancery the like ſum of tenne pound: And to Miſtris <hi>Sut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> of London widdow the ſumme of three pound ſixe ſhillings eight pence to make her a Ring.</p>
            <p>Alſo he gaue to Maiſter <hi>Hutton</hi> Clarke &amp; Vicar of Littlebury the aduowſion or next preſentation to the parſonage of Dunsby in the County of Lincolne.</p>
            <p>Alſo he did then publiſh and declare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Maiſter <hi>Flud</hi> Parſon of Stoke-New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ington in the County of Middleſex <hi>Robert Petit Alexander Longworth Iohn Parſons</hi> and <hi>Thomas Iohnſon</hi> his cooke that he had made his will and thereof had made and ordaind <hi>Richard Sutton</hi> of London Eſquire and <hi>Iohn Lawe</hi> his Executors.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
